<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A00.sch" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<Product_Bundle xmlns="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1 https://pds.nasa.gov/pds4/pds/v1/PDS4_PDS_1A00.xsd">
  <Identification_Area>
    <logical_identifier>urn:nasa:pds:tno-centaur_diam-albedo-density</logical_identifier>
    <version_id>1.0</version_id>
    <title>TNO AND CENTAUR DIAMETERS, ALBEDOS, AND DENSITIES V1.0</title>
    <information_model_version>1.10.0.0</information_model_version>
    <product_class>Product_Bundle</product_class>
    <Citation_Information>
      <author_list>Johnston, W. R.</author_list>
      <publication_year>2018</publication_year>
      <description>This data set is a compilation of published diameters, albedos, and densities for
Transneptunian Objects (TNOs) and Centaurs.  A total of 194 objects are listed, many
with more than one entry.  This version covers published values through 31 March
2018.</description>
    </Citation_Information>
  </Identification_Area>
  <Context_Area>
    <Time_Coordinates>
      <start_date_time>1986-01-01Z</start_date_time>
      <stop_date_time>2018-03-31Z</stop_date_time>
    </Time_Coordinates>
    <Investigation_Area>
      <name>None</name>
      <type>Individual Investigation</type>
      <Internal_Reference>
        <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:context:investigation:individual.none</lid_reference>
        <reference_type>bundle_to_investigation</reference_type>
      </Internal_Reference>
    </Investigation_Area>
  </Context_Area>
  <Bundle>
    <bundle_type>Archive</bundle_type>
    <description>OVERVIEW                                                                  
                                                                            
  This data set is a compilation of published diameters, albedos, and       
  densities for Transneptunian Objects (TNOs) and Centaurs.  A total of 194 
  objects are listed, many with more than one entry.  This version covers   
  published values through 31 March 2018.                                   
                                                                            
  DATA                                                                      
                                                                            
  Data were collected from the published literature for TNOs and Centaurs,  
  with many objects having data reported by more than one group.  Reported  
  values for Pluto and Charon are limited to those published after 1985.    
  Entries are listed by object permanent number, then by provisional        
  designation, then by year of publication, then alphabetically by          
  author(s).  Users are referred to the respective papers regarding details 
  of observations and methodology.                                          
                                                                            
                                                                            
  TABLES                                                                    
                                                                            
  The table 'tno_centaur_diam_alb_dens' lists data for objects with the     
  following columns:                                                        
                                                                            
     * object number, name, and provisional designation;                    
     * object heliocentric semimajor axis (AU), eccentricity, and           
    inclination;                                                            
     * object dynamical type;                                               
     * number of known companions;                                          
     * MPC-reported absolute magnitude (as of 31 March 2016);               
     * absolute magnitude value used in albedo calculation with error bar;  
     * effective diameter (km) with upper/lower error bars and note code;   
     * primary diameter (km) with upper/lower error bars and note code;     
     * companion diameter (km) with upper/lower error bars and note code;   
     * albedo with upper/lower error bars, note code, and color code;       
     * system mass density (g/cm^3) with upper/lower error bars and note    
    code;                                                                   
     * methods used for diameter/albedo determination and density           
    determination;                                                          
     * and reference code.                                                  
                                                                            
  Dynamical type codes are as follows:                                      
     1:2 = Neptune 1:2 resonance object,                                    
     2:5 = Neptune 2:5 resonance object,                                    
     2:7 = Neptune 2:7 resonance object,                                    
     3:5 = Neptune 3:5 resonance object,                                    
     3:8 = Neptune 3:8 resonance object,                                    
     3:10 = Neptune 3:10 resonance object,                                  
     4:7 = Neptune 4:7 resonance object,                                    
     CEN = Centaur,                                                         
     CUB = Cubewano,                                                        
     HAU = Haumea family,                                                   
     NL4 = Neptune trojan, L4 position,                                     
     PLU = Plutino (= Neptune 2:3 resonance object),                        
     SAT = satellite,                                                       
     SDO = scattered disk object, and                                       
     TNO = other Transneptunian Object.                                     
  Dynamical types are based on the Minor Planet Center 'Unusual Minor       
  Planet' listings and on classifications by the Deep Ecliptic Survey Team  
  [http://www.boulder.swri.edu/~buie/kbo/desclass.html] (see Elliot et al., 
  2005).  Haumea family members are those listed by Snodgrass et al., 2010. 
                                                                            
  For single objects, effective diameter is the measured diameter and the   
  component diameter columns have null values.  For objects with more than  
  one component, effective diameter is the combined effective diameter      
  (where D_eff^2 = D_1^2 + D_2^2 for binaries, etc.) and individual         
  component diameters are provided in the respective columns.  In general,  
  albedo and density values are the system averages; if they are specific to
  a component, they include a note code specifying which component (1, 2, 3,
  ...) in a separate entry for that component.  Separate entries are also   
  provided for additional components after the first two, again with note   
  codes specifying which component (3, 4, ...).                             
                                                                            
  Note codes indicate comments on data values as follows (more than one code
  may apply):                                                               
     1, 2, 3, ... = component diameter for first, second, third, etc.,      
    system component;                                                       
     A = assumed, applies to adopted values used from other publications or 
    to assumed densities used for dynamical determinations of               
    diameter/albedo;                                                        
     D = derived by the compiler from values reported by the respective     
    source;                                                                 
     G = greater than;                                                      
     L = less than;                                                         
                                                                            
  Albedo color codes indicate color reported by the source:  B = blue, R =  
     red, V = visual, and * = geometric (no color specified).               
                                                                            
  Method codes for diameter/albedo determinations are as follows (more than 
  one code may apply):                                                      
     E = mutual events;                                                     
     I = direct imaging;                                                    
     M = multiple or modified methods (see respective source for details);  
     O = stellar occultation;                                               
     T = thermal/radiometric observations/modeling;                         
     Y = dynamical (based on system mass from orbit determination, observed 
    magnitude, and assumed density;                                         
     # = cited source reported only system mass, values given here are      
    derived;                                                                
     * = reanalysis of previously published results.                        
                                                                            
  Method codes for density determinations are as follows (more than one code
  may apply):                                                               
     H = hydrodynamic model (based on observed/derived oblateness).         
     M = multiple or modified methods (see respective source for details);  
     Y = dynamical (based on system mass from orbit determination and       
    independently measured diameter);                                       
     * = reanalysis of previously published results.                        
                                                                            
  Reference codes refer to full reference information listed in the         
  'references' table.  This table has columns for reference code and full   
  reference.                                                                
                                                                            
  Regarding uncertainties on measured values, readers are referred to the   
  respective references.  Dashes or invalid inputs (usually -9.99) indicate 
  unassigned or unknown values.                                             
                                                                            
                                                                            
  MODIFICATION HISTORY                                                      
                                                                            
  Differences between the current database version and the previous version 
  (2016) are:                                                               
                                                                            
     * A total of 194 objects/systems are represented, or 4 more than the   
    previous release.                                                       
     * A total of 652 entries are included, or 70 more than the previous    
    release.                                                                
     * Heliocentric orbit semimajor axis, eccentricity, and inclination are 
    updated from the MPC Orbit (MPCORB) Database, and outer solar system    
    dynamical types are supplemented by classifications from the Deep       
    Ecliptic Survey Team.                                                   
                                                                            
  Modifications in successive versions are summarized as follows:           
     * V1.0 in PDS3 (31 March 2013) contained 341 entries representing 125 objects/ 
    systems and included object number, name, and provisional designation;  
    heliocentric semimajor axis, eccentricity, inclination, and dynamical   
    type; number of known companions; absolute magnitude from MPC and as    
    used in albedo calculations; effective diameter and (for binary/        
    multiple objects) primary and secondary diameters; albedo, system mass  
    density, codes for methods used, and reference codes.                   
     * V2.0 (31 March 2014) contained 519 entries representing 178 objects/ 
    systems.                                                                
     * V3.0 (31 March 2015) contained 549 entries representing 181 objects/ 
    systems.                                                                
     * V4.0 (31 March 2016) contained 582 entries representing 190 objects/ 
    systems.                                                                
     * V1.0 in PDS4 (31 March 2018) contains 652 entries representing 194 objects/  
    systems.                                                                
                                                                            
                                                                            
  JOURNALS USED                                                             
                                                                            
  Cited sources include articles from the following journals:  Astronomy and
  Astrophysics; Astronomical Journal; Astrophysical Journal; Astrophysical  
  Journal Letters; Bulletin of the American Astronomical Society; Earth,    
  Moon and Planets; Icarus; Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical       
  Society; Nature; Publications of the Astronomical Society of the Pacific; 
  and Science.  Other sources are from conference proceedings, IAUCs, and   
  book contributions.                                                       
                                                                            
                                                                            
  REFERENCES                                                                
                                                                            
  Elliot, J. L., et al., 2005, The Deep Ecliptic Survey:  A search for      
  Kuiper belt objects and Centaurs. II. Dynamical classification, the Kuiper
  belt plane, and the core population, Astron. J., 129:1117-1162.           
                                                                            
  Snodgrass, C., B. Carry, C. Dumas, and O. Hainaut, 2010, Characterisation 
  of candidate members of (136108) Haumea's family, Astron. &amp; Astrophys.,   
  511:A72.</description>
  </Bundle>
  <Bundle_Member_Entry>
    <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:tno-centaur_diam-albedo-density:data</lid_reference>
    <member_status>Primary</member_status>
    <reference_type>bundle_has_data_collection</reference_type>
  </Bundle_Member_Entry>
  <Bundle_Member_Entry>
    <lid_reference>urn:nasa:pds:tno-centaur_diam-albedo-density:document</lid_reference>
    <member_status>Primary</member_status>
    <reference_type>bundle_has_document_collection</reference_type>
  </Bundle_Member_Entry>
</Product_Bundle>

